Let’s say you really need
to find reliable information
about the best diet for
high blood pressure,
or heart disease,
or diabetes.
Where do you go?
Do you go to a website
sponsored by Big Pharma
that wants to sell you
pills to fix your problem?
Or, do you want
to treat the cause?
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast
with the latest peer-
reviewed research
on the best ways to eat
healthy and live longer.
Today we bring you some important
research on processed meat,
which has been classified
as a Group 1 carcinogen.
How did the meat
industry, government,
and cancer organizations
respond to that news?
Here’s our first story.
“It is [perhaps] rare, in
the history of nations,
that one finds good reasons
to render homage to the
generosity and altruism of
governments and those in power,
but the birth of the International
Agency for Research on Cancer
(IARC) presents one
of those rare occasions.”
It all started with a single
letter from a bereaved husband,
relating the suffering of his
wife after a cancer diagnosis,
cascading into this open
letter calling for governments
to devote half of 1 percent
of their military budgets
to fight for life, by attacking
one of the greatest plagues
that weigh on humanity.
And 18 months later,
the IARC was born
in the World Health Organization.
With what overarching motive?
Cancer prevention.
The IARC is best known for its
monographs, book-sized reports
evaluating whether or not
some suspected carcinogen does
in fact cause cancer.
They are generally accepted
as close to a ﬁnal word
as there is on whether or
not something is carcinogenic.
And their 114th monograph,
published in 2018, was on meat.
After thoroughly reviewing the
accumulated scientific literature,
a Working Group of 22
experts from 10 countries,
after considering more
than 800 different studies,
concluded their 500-page
report by establishing that
something like a burger or pork
chop is probably carcinogenic,
probably causes cancer.
But processed meat was
placed as a Group 1 carcinogen,
the highest level of certainty,
meaning that according
to the best available
evidence the consumption
of processed meat causes cancer.
So, that means foods
like bacon cause cancer;
ham, hot dogs, breakfast links,
lunch meat cause cancer.
But their definition also
includes, for example,
turkey deli slices.
Specifically, eating processed
meat causes colorectal cancer,
cancers of the colon or
rectum, the second most deadly
cancer worldwide, after lung cancer
which is caused largely from smoking.
Colorectal cancer is the second
leading cause of cancer death
here in the United States as well,
and it doesn’t just strike older people.
It’s also a leading cause
of cancer and death
from cancer earlier in life as well.
The meat industry wasn’t
happy, calling it
a “dramatic and alarmist overreach.”
Speaking of dramatic and
alarmist overreach,
one ag group in Italy
sent out a press release:
Just say no to terrorism on meat.
The gloves were off.
The meat industry in Canada
tried to pressure the government
to cut off funds to the IARC,
asking the Health Minister
to pull all funding from the agency
after they dared to question meat.
And the U.S. meat industry
did the same thing.
It’s no surprise the IARC is
under siege by corporate interests,
trying to challenge
their cancer evaluations
on Monsanto’s Roundup
pesticide and meat;
trying to discredit the agency
and undermine financial support.
Internal documents have revealed
that Monsanto scientists,
for example, “casually
discussing ‘ghost-writing’
scientific papers and
suppressing any science that
conflicts with the company’s
assertions of safety.”
The chemical industry has
joined the corporate cacophony,
calling the IARC monographs
“dubious and misleading.”
These are classic strategies
straight out of the
tobacco industry playbook.
“But there is little to suggest
that, as a corporate actor,
’Big Tobacco‘ differs
fundamentally from
’Big Booze’ or ’Big Food’", for example.
One recurring corporate talking
point is that basically
the IARC never met a
carcinogen it didn’t like.
But the vast majority end up
being categorized as just
possibly carcinogenic, or there
really aren’t sufficient data
to make a determination either way.
And look, they only spend
time looking at substances
for which there is
already an existing body of
scientific literature
indicating a degree
of carcinogenic hazard to humans;
so, no wonder many of them
end up, indeed, carcinogenic.
How did the IARC respond
to all the criticism?
The World Health Organization
received a number of queries,
expressions of concern,
and requests for clarification
following the publication of
their meat and cancer report.
They replied, hey we never
told anyone to stop eating
processed meats—
your body your choice.
They just indicated that
reducing consumption of these
products can reduce the risk
of a leading cancer killer.
So hey, you like cancer? You do you.
The IARC is just a research
organization that evaluates
the evidence on the causes of cancer;
after that, what you do with
that information is up to you.
The American Cancer
Society was nice
and clear when it came to alcohol.
When it comes to cancer, it
is best not to drink alcohol.
But they got a little more
wishy-washy with processed meat,
suggesting people can get away
with just limiting their intake.
The European Commission
was a little clearer.
To reduce our risk of cancer
we should eat plenty of
whole grains, pulses
(which are beans, split peas,
chickpeas and lentils),
vegetables and fruits,
limit sugary, fatty, salty
foods, and straight-up avoid
soda, sausage, and
other processed meats.
After all, in answering
the question how much meat
is safe to eat, the IARC
replied that we don’t yet know
whether a safe level exists, period.
In this next story, I quantify the
risks of colon and rectal cancers
from eating foods like bacon,
ham, hot dogs, sausage, and lunch meat.
In 2018, arguably the most
prestigious cancer research institution
in the world, the International Agency
for Research on Cancer (IARC),
within the World Health Organization,
published their report
on processed meat, concluding
that foods like bacon, ham,
hot dogs, lunch meat, and
sausages are cancer causing,
classifying processed meat
as a Group 1 carcinogen.
“These findings,” concluded
the director of the agency,
“further support current
public health recommendations
to limit the intake of meat.”
Critics questioned putting
processed meat in the same
carcinogenic classification
as asbestos or tobacco.
Or as a pesticide company
roughly put it, how can eating
processed meat fall into the
same category as mustard gas.
The classifications only relate
to the strength of evidence
that the agent causes cancer
or not, not how much cancer.
This does not mean that
they are all equally dangerous.
It’s safer to eat a sandwich
filled with pastrami than plutonium,
even though they are both
Group 1 carcinogens;
both substances known to
cause cancer in people.
Okay, so just how
dangerous is meat?
The relative risk of colorectal
cancer was 18 percent
for every 50 grams a day. Okay,
so what exactly does that mean?
Well, 50 grams is about one hot
dog, or two breakfast links,
or two slices of
Canadian bacon or ham.
So, a daily sandwich with one
or two slices of baloney
would increase your colorectal
cancer risk by 18 percent.
But a half-pound
pastrami on rye would
bump it up more like 80 percent.
Okay, but what does the 18 percent
increased risk really mean?
One way to look at it is
absolute risk versus relative risk.
Assuming that the lifetime
risk of colorectal cancer is
about 5 percent (1 in 20),
increasing your risk about
20 percent would only
bump up your absolute risk
of getting colorectal cancer
from 5 percent to 6 percent.
Now, on a population scale,
an 18 percent drop in risk
could mean about 25,000 fewer
cases of colorectal cancer
every year in the United States,
25,000 fewer families a year
dealing with that diagnosis,
if we swapped out the daily
sandwich for hummus or
chose veggie dogs instead.
So, it all depends on
how you look at it.
Colorectal cancer is our second
leading cause of cancer death
for men and women combined,
after lung cancer.
So, if you don’t smoke,
colon and rectal cancer
may be your greatest cancer nemesis.
But we can drop the risk
of getting it by about a fifth
with a single dietary tweak:
cutting a serving of
processed meat out of our daily diet.
How does 18 percent
increased cancer risk
compare to other risky behavior?
In my testimony before the Dietary
Guidelines Scientific Committee,
I made what may sound
like a hyperbolic metaphor.
I asked, “We try not to
smoke around our kids,
why would we send them to
school with a baloney sandwich?”
That is not hyperbole.
According to the Surgeon
General, living with a smoker
increases your risk of
lung cancer by 15 percent.
So, breathing second-hand
smoke day in and day out
increases your risk of lung
cancer almost as much as
eating a serving of processed
meat day in and day out
increases your risk
of colorectal cancer.
The meat industry responded
by saying that the risks
and benefits must be
considered together before
telling people what to eat or breathe.
Think about all the baloney benefits.
Lunch meat isn’t just about
cancer but convenience.
Indeed, processed meat
isn’t just about cancer.
An article railing against
the World Health Organization’s
“meat terrorism” cited the
Global Burden of Disease studies
comparing how many cancer deaths
are caused by processed meat
consumption compared to
tobacco or alcohol use.
But if you look at the
study they’re referencing,
the 30-something thousand
deaths attributable to higher
processed meat intake are
just the colorectal cancer deaths,
and don’t also include the
100,000 deaths from diabetes
or the 400,000 deaths from heart disease.
So, in actuality, we may be
talking a half million deaths
attributable to processed meat.
And it’s not just
colon and rectal cancer.
If you look at the science since
the IARC decision was published,
processed meat may also
increase the risk of
prostate cancer, breast cancer,
and pancreatic cancer.
Unfortunately, despite growing
public health concerns
about processed meat consumption,
there have been no changes
in the amount of processed
meat consumed by U.S. adults
over the last 18 years.
Of course, it would
have helped if the last
Dietary Guidelines for Americans
had happened to mention
that processed meat was a carcinogen.
An explicit and science-based
statement on processed meat
in the next Dietary Guidelines
would certainly help.
But the scientific committee
made no such recommendation.
Sadly, even those diagnosed with
colorectal cancer hardly improve
their overall lifestyle after
diagnosis, though that may be
because “70 percent of cancer
patients had never received
nutrition advice from
their [medical] providers
during or after treatment.”
That just blows me away.
“Despite the continued
obfuscation of the issue
by the meat industry—they learned
well from the tobacco merchants—
meat should continue to be
a focus of public health action.”
New York City is leading
the way, passing legislation
to ban processed meats
from school meals.
What a concept, not giving
our kids carcinogens.
Meanwhile, the processed
meat industry
is trying to reformulate its products.
It’s kind of like in
the pharmaceutical area,
where you try to mitigate
the potential adverse effects
of one drug by prescribing
an additional drug.
Like you could add fiber to
hot dogs or something to try
to counterbalance the risk,
potentially reducing the cancer load
by changing how it’s
processed rather than by
banning processed meat altogether.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite to each of these topics.
For a timely text on the
pathogens that cause pandemics,
order the e-book,
audiobook, or hard copy
of my last book,
“How to Survive a Pandemic”.
For recipes, check out
my second-to-last book,
my “How Not to Diet Cookbook”.
It’s beautifully designed
with more than 100 recipes
for delicious and
nutritious meals.
And all the proceeds
I receive from the sales
of all my books goes to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the website is free.
There’s no ads, no corporate sponsorship.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.